The thing that was so disturbing about
the bust is that after 60 years of war
on drugs, you had customs agents who
still didn't know the difference between
cocoa and cocaine after expending a
trillion dollars on this failed
campaign. And that was really the
equivalent, if you think about it, of
Elliot Nest busting a truckload of
potatoes in violation of the Volstead
Act. You know, cocoa is to cocaine what
potatoes are to vodka.
>> I thought Andy, we could start with the
ethnobotanical
medicinal side of things.
>> Mhm.
>> Because I'll share perhaps an anecdote
to kick us off, which was I, as both of
you have have spent a lot of time in
South America, and it's not always to
end up in the lower upper Amazon
consuming questionable substances. It's
sometimes to do other things like visit
cities and spend time with friends and
go skiing.
>> And the skiing in this case was in Chile
and it was the first instance where we
landed in Santiago, drove to elevation
very quickly and I had my first
experience with terrible altitude
sickness. And for those who have not
experienced it, I do not wish it upon my
worst enemy. It is an absolutely
horrific
experience. It's terrible. And
even though the legal status I think is
a question mark or maybe it's very
directly
verboten in Chile, the locals in the
lodge gave me coca leaf tea and within
several hours no symptoms and they did
not recur past that point which blew my
mind particularly since even with Diamox
to help with altitude acclamation my
experience has been that it takes a few
days and I did not have any good way to
explain this particularly given my
levels of exertion
>> and not surprisingly in other countries
whether it's Peru, Colombia certainly if
you look at the Kogis and so on this
plant is not just incredibly important
from a
let's just call it for lack of a better
term religious perspective, cultural
perspective, but also medicinal
perspective. So, I was hoping Andy you
could give a primer on what makes Koka
the plant interesting.
>> Well, let me say I first met Koka in
1965.
I just finished my first year of medical
school and my mentor Dick Schulties who
was director of the Harvard Botanical
Museum sent me to South America to
collect medicinal plants with one of his
graduate students in the Amazon in the
Andes. And I met with him right before I
left and he said, "When you're in Peru,
be sure to chew cocoa." [laughter] He
said, "It's a very interesting plant and
you want to learn about it." So I did
and I have been using cocoa ever since.
And my original interest was to find out
how this was used by indigenous peoples
medically. It's as important to that
population as peppermint and chamomile
are in European medicine. you know it's
their major medicinal plant and the main
indication is for treating GI disorders
but it also it is obviously relied on to
provide energy in doing physical work to
help with altitude sickness as you
mentioned to boost mood and to improve
metabolism.
The population the Andes especially is
often not wellnourished
and they eat a very high starch diet.
They have um high incidence of genes
predisposing them to type two diabetes.
But they don't have diabetes if they are
on their traditional diets and
exercising and chewing cocoa. But if
they move to lower altitude and stop
chewing cocoa and eat more like the
blanco population in Peru, they develop
very high rates of type 2 diabetes. So
that's quite interesting. you know that
it has some normalizing effect on blood
sugar and metabolism which is something
that I'd really like to see good
research on. So I think there are
multiple uses and these are not
attributable to effects of cocaine and I
think this is most important that in
cocoa there are 14 alkaloids. Cocaine is
one of them and they all have similar
chemical structures and none of them
have ever been studied. You know once we
isolated cocaine from the leaf everybody
lost interest in everything else. So, we
don't really know what those other
things do and how they modify the
activity of cocaine. The amount of
cocaine in coke is relatively small. You
know, it would not be worth anybody's
time on a home scale to try to extract
cocaine from cocoa. You need a tonnage
of leaves to get a significant amount.
But I [snorts] think the most important
point is that this whole complex of
compounds acting together is responsible
for the effects that you know people
report as being very beneficial both for
mental health and physical health.
>> Could you say more about the digestive
or metabolic effects? Do we have an idea
of the mechanism of action there? What
it's actually doing? Coke has been
remarkably little studied. For a plant
of such enormous historical, cultural,
economic, scientific, medical
importance, there is an almost complete
absence of research on it. And Wade can
talk about the reasons for that. But one
of the things that struck me when I was
interviewing people in the Andes about
the GI effects was that the respondents
said that it treated both diarrhea and
constipation. That doesn't make any
sense from the point of view of Western
pharmacology. Cocaine is a gut
stimulant. So obviously be great for
constipation, but it couldn't do
anything for diarrhea except make it
worse. And that always puzzled me. But
then looking at these other cocoa
alkyoids, there's something peculiar
about them. If you look at the
structural formula of the molecules,
they resemble drugs like atropene and
scapalamine which are found in
nightshade plants and those are gut
paralytics. Scapalamine has been used in
medicine to treat diarrhea. So this is
kind of a paradox. You've got a molecule
that just from its shape you predict
would be a gut paralytic, but in fact
cocaine is a is a gut stimulant. So how
does this work? I think you know this is
a model for the differences between a
whole plant drug and an isolated
compound. I think when you present the
body with this mix of
ambivalent
molecules you know that they push and
they pull against physiology the body
decides what it wants to use. And that's
not attributing mystical intelligence to
the body. It may be which receptors are
available for binding at the moment. So
if there is an overactive gut motility,
it selects the ones that slow that down.
That's fascinating to me that Koka has
this sort of paradoxical activity and
lets the body can choose which action it
wants.
>> Mhm. [clears throat] So beyond let's
just say you know the motility making
bowel movement regular for lack of a
better descriptor is it ever used by
indigenous populations for what we might
consider illnesses like Crohn's disease
or irritable bowel syndrome I don't even
know what the occurrence of those things
would be in such populations but is it
used for other indications
>> it is the great remedy for all GI
disorders and also they believe that it
helps them utilize
the nutritional qualities of foods that
they consume.
>> They often feel that if they don't
follow like a meal, one of their high
starch meals with a chew of cocoa that
they don't metabolize it well. There has
been almost no research on this, but
there was one really interesting study
done with Andian Indians, having them
ride exercise bikes and measuring blood
sugar at intervals after they gave them
a glucose load. And at any point in the
cycle where they began to choka, blood
sugar would normalize. So, this is just
one study that was done some time ago.
And I I mean gosh that should just call
out for a whole lot more work of that
kind. Yeah, that's fascinating.
>> Yeah, super fascinating. So I wanted to
just mention a few things for folks
pulling from what you just said. So you
mentioned Dick Shalties. If people don't
recognize the name Richard Evan
Schulties, I guess that's what s ces.
Look him up. Do yourself a favor and
look up Richard Evans Schulty's. The bio
on Richard
>> and Wade was his graduate student.
Exactly.
>> I worked with him as an undergraduate,
but that's how Wade and I first met
through him.
>> Just incredible. And I may come back to
the peppermint chamomile sidebar that
you had because
that seems interesting in and of itself.
But but to your point of isolated
components of a plant versus the whole
plant, there are many historical
examples of this. one that we could pull
from that
can show perhaps the pitfalls of
isolation. Not to say there aren't
applications of isolations, right? It's
better to take something like aspirin
than white willow bark perhaps. But if
scientists came to the premature
conclusion that well, if consuming foods
with betaarotene seems to be supportive
to vision, why don't we just mainline
>> isolated betaarotene turns out not to be
a great idea. Right. Right.
>> There's a lot more research needed.
Wade, do you want to speak to your first
introduction encounter with Koka and
perhaps speak to why rehabilitation is
even needed? I think some people might
jump to the conclusions like well
cocaine drug trade period end of story,
but I suspect there's probably more
there.
>> Well, you know, the thing is Tim, I
mean, coke has been used in South
America by virtually every culture of
the Andine and Northwest Amazon for
8,000 years. And during that time,
there's been no evidence whatsoever of
any toxicity, let alone addiction. My
first encounter was actually with Tim
Plowman, a good friend of Andes, who
introduced me to Andy, who had a great
grant through Schulties to study coke in
the 1970s. And it spoke to the fact what
Andy said is how little was known about
the plant. To me, one of the most
astonishing things is that the plant had
been demonized from the 1920s. And yet,
no one had ever bothered to do a
nutritional study until Tim and Jim Duke
did that and published in 1975. And Andy
was sort of on part of that team. And
the results were extraordinary. Not only
did it have a modest amount of the
alkyoid absorbed benignly in the mucous
membrane of the mouth, but it was chalk
full of vitamins and proteins, more
calcium than any other plant studied. As
Andy alluded to it, enzymes that perhaps
enhance the ability of the body to
digest carbohydrate at high elevation.
This was food and medicine, utterly
benign. And the question comes, why
didn't someone do a study? And they
didn't do a study because they didn't
want to know. And I think the single
most disturbing fact about cocoa is that
the efforts to eradicate the fields, the
traditional fields of cocoa began 60
years before there was a cocaine
problem. It had nothing to do with the
pharmacology of cocaine hydrochloride
and everything to do with the cultural
identity of the indigenous people who
revered the plant. And what happened is
physicians in Lima in particular looked
up into the Andes and they saw social
pathologies of literacy, poor nutrition,
poverty, and because issues of economics
and land reform and real economic
justice challenged the foundation of
their bourgeoa lives in Lima, they had
to find a culprit and they settled on
Koka.
>> My observation is that Peru is actually
a country with two nations within it.
There is the white European nation with
its capital at Lima that has alcohol as
its preferred psychoactive drug and
there's the indigenous population mostly
living at high altitude and some in the
Amazon that rely on cocoa and those two
cultures have been at war with each
other ever since. And I think that for
the Europeans coca chewing became a
symbol of indigenous culture and
everything they didn't like. And what
they would love to see is either
eradicate that culture or have it turn
into the same as them.
>> Well, I mean these efforts were really
pernitious and based on pseudocience.
And during all those years, including a
famous commission dispatched in the late
1940s by the UN to study the so-called
Koka problem. That commission led by a
man called Howard Fonda who was a
pharmaceutical executive announced its
conclusions before leaving New York. and
upon arrival in Lemur reiterated word
for word those same conclusions that the
plant had be eradicated and they spent
three months in the southern Andes
meeting with military officials ales
government officials priests they didn't
interview a single traditional user of
the leaf and naturally they concluded
that this plant had to be eradicated and
I think if you really look at the
language that they used it was not just
dark it was racist And that alludes to
what Andy is saying that until recently
Latin America, not just Peru, is very
much a place of conqueror and conquered.
And Koka became the symbol of everything
indigenous and therefore shameful to
these elites.
>> Wade, do you want to say something about
the recent WH study, which is a
continuation of all this? incredibly
this condemnation of Koka was in
language that was just so dark and
racist. And the amazing thing though is
that these very people with their
pseudocientific studies and their
hideous approach and language were the
very ones who wrote the language of the
regulations and conventions that dictate
international drug policy to this day,
including the 1961 UN Declaration on
Narcotic Drugs. And in all of this time,
there have been no effort to actually
identify the real value of the plant.
And efforts have been underway more
recently to get cocoa descheduled or
rescheduled. In the UN system, cocoa
leaf is now scheduled alongside with
fentanyl and heroin as among the most
dangerous drugs in the world. And the
efforts that we've been trying to do is
to get it to either be scheduled to the
point where it's seen to be of problems
but medicinal [clears throat] potential
or better yet descheduled altogether so
that we can create elicit market for the
plant. And here's the reason for that.
We have 250,000 families in Colombia
that grow cocoa to survive. We need to
give them elicit outlet for their
product.
Columbia as a nation needs the revenue,
the tax revenue that can come from the
international commercialization of the
leave to pay for the cost of peace,
having drained its treasury for 60 years
to pay the costs of a war that would
have not lasted a day without the sorted
profits of prohibition. And above all,
the world's population has a right to
benefit from this plant. You know, we
have an enormous substance abuse problem
in our country and a lot of it has to do
with stimulant abuse.
>> There's also the problem of the I think
the reckless prescribing of stimulants
to kids.
>> Andy, could I ask you to bookmark that
for a second cuz I want to give people a
window into cocoa leaf. Okay. So they
understand the subjective experience for
a second.
>> Sure.
>> In Peru and other places, I mean,
shocking to me. I think it was in Peru
where I saw they were selling boxes of
cocoa leaf tea in the international
departures
wing and I was like guys I want to take
this with me but I can't. The subjective
effect of drinking cocoa leaf tea is a
among other things a stimulant effect
that is far less for me than a half a
cup of coffee but without the subsequent
crash that may be due to any number of
things. I think it could be a glucose
spike and then sort of subsequent crash
but it is very very very mild.
>> Okay. Now I have to say that cocoa leaf
tea is not the most efficient way to use
cocoa.
>> No it isn't. It isn't.
>> The traditional way is to hold leaves in
your mouth.
>> Yeah.
>> Moisten them. Add an alkali which
promotes absorption of the alkaloids and
let it slowly diffuse into the
bloodstream. Mhm.
>> Now, I don't think people up here are
going to chew a mouthful of leaves, but
you know, I've always thought we could
make a lozenge or a chewing gum that
would reproduce that effect.
>> Well, you could have a snooze packet
like nicotine, right?
>> Yeah. Right. Exactly. But the stimulant
effect is so much milder, and Wade can
talk to this too, I think, than coffee,
for example, or than any of the
pharmaceutical stimulants. The really
fascinating literature is in the late
19th century when physicians traveling
in Peru were aware of the hazards of
cocaine but not yet judging the leaves
reflexively. And the reports have this
ingenuous quality to him. Like I mean
there's one from the head of the British
Medical Association who was 78 years old
and he gots up in the morning, walks
halfway across Scotland, climbs a
mountain, gets down, doesn't eat all day
and says, "Well, that was quite a day."
In other words, there's this Mortimer
calls it like the stimulant that's not a
stimulant. And so this is really the way
the plant operates, the subtlety of it.
You don't feel you're stimulated. You
just recognize the results of having
been able to focus, concentrate, and
remain at task in a creative way through
a long period of time. We do a little
thought experiment. If I told you there
was a plant that you could take that
gave you a slight lightness of being, a
slight kind of skip in your step, a
sense of well-being that eliminated all
the sort of existential little neurosis
that we all suffer as conscious beings,
and it allowed you to focus at task,
whatever that creative task was, whether
it was a spinning of wool or the writing
of digital code, and you could sit at
task all day long, concentrating on task
with immense focus.
with no sense of being under the
influence of any plant, nothing as harsh
as a second cup of coffee, and you found
yourself at the end of the day ready to
go home, have dinner, and do it all over
again the next day. The truth is that
cocoa has this capacity to improve our
lives. It also helps with weight
management, Tim, because it makes you
less hungry and feeling like you want to
move. So that is a very desirable thing
that many people would find useful and I
think the mood elevating effects of
cocoa are very significant.
>> Let me ask a question on the mind of a
lot of listeners. I'll also just add in
I have used the sort of mouth buckle in
the form of goes by a million different
names you know mambbe or whatever and
even in that case very very mild
>> and what I would say if I were to
compare it to other things as my
long-term listeners might imagine I've
tried medapanyl I've tried the various
empetamines you know aderall rolin etc
and the difference is that number one
you have thousands of years of human use
documented in the case of cocoa.
Secondly, I did not seem to develop any
type I'm sure you do develop some
tolerance. But for instance, if I use
medafanyl for 2 or 3 days and I stop, I
immediately feel a physical requirement
to use it to get back to my prior
baseline. And that does not happen in
the case of cocoa. It certainly happens
in the case of caffeine for me
>> and cocaine.
>> And cocaine. But the question I want to
ask is, you know, Wade, you mentioned
this enormous number of families
dependent on growing cocoa. On an
individual level, I can see how, hey, if
you ship me a small box of coca leaf for
my personal use, there's no way I'm
going to convert that into cocaine. But
how do you on a national level if these
farms are pre-existing decouple the the
good of listenit cocoa while
simultaneously constraining the evils of
cocaine production? Is that possible?
>> Well, I mean the thing there is that the
status of cocoa has no relevance
whatsoever to the cartels. With cocoa as
a prohibited substance, they've made
fortunes shipping cocaine by the ton for
50 years in the United States. And where
cocoa leaves to be legal with a listenit
commercial export market, you would
still maintain the same controls over
the illicit production of cocaine that
you have today. So it's kind of
irrelevant. The critical thing is that
crop substitution programs are an
illusion because how do you transport to
market cacao or bananas when you can
take cocoa paste and put it in your
muila and walk down the trail? And so
this expansion of cocoa production is
going on dramatically and it's having
huge impacts on tropical rainforest. So
deforestation since the peace agreement
in Colombia is very disturbing. And yet
we have millions of acres of already cut
over land that we could cultivate cocoa
on for the well-being of the people. And
you know, I think it's worth just
thinking about the history of this
plant, 8,000 years. One of the most
amazing things about cocoa is that it's
been domesticated not once, not twice,
but three separate times in human
history. That is unheard of. And Tim, I
think, you know, one um approach to the
problem you brought up is education,
which I'm a great believer in. I think
if people knew what cocoa was and
understood its benefits, they would
demand it. They'd want it. And that
includes even people who use cocaine. I
have known a number of people who got
strung out on cocaine and experienced a
lot of negative effects from it. And
when they tried coca and used it
properly, they saw that it was a much
more desirable state and they didn't
want to use cocaine anymore. So I think
that's something we could do. By the
way, it should also mention that through
an accident of history, cocoa is in
schedule two of the controlled
substances act, not schedule one like
cannabis and psychedelics. It got there
and schedule 2 is substances that have a
high potential for abuse but have
recognized therapeutic application. It's
only there because cocaine has limited
uses as a medical drug in athalmology
and dentistry.
But that makes it a little easier, you
know, to leverage cocoa out of that
controlled substance box.
>> It's just a matter of demonstrating that
there are therapeutic applications that
the FDA could approve.
>> All right. So, I want to fill in a gap
and then come back to problem solving.
But before we get to the problem solving
and policy work, I'll plant a seed,
which is if these farmers suddenly could
legally
ship product that for export or domestic
use in the form of cocoa, could they
actually get around the cartel or would
they be putting a bullseye on their
forehead? That's a question not for now,
but for later. What I'd like to talk
about first is the
indigenous cultural context in which
koka is used and its importance right
because as you mentioned I mean it's not
exactly ubiquitous in South America but
in a handful of countries
I mean cocoa is considered
for lack of a better term a master plant
right a sacred plant. There are four
different varieties that Tim Plowman
identified of cultivated cocoa. Two
species each with two different
varieties. And we now know that from DNA
analysis that the progenitor of all four
varieties was a wild cocoa called
aeriththroam graasalipes that grows
along the eastern flanks of the Andes de
la all the way from Venezuela down to
Bolivia. And what this means is that at
three times in pre-colian history, human
beings came upon this delicate little
shrub in the forest with fruits the
color and the size of rubies and
beautiful little white flowers and
delicate foliage and said that's the
one. And it was domesticated three times
in the Montana of Colombia, in the
jungus of La Pas and Bolivia and Peru,
and in the northwest Amazon. And that is
extremely rare in the history of plant
domestication.
And not only was it domesticated three
times, everywhere it was domesticated,
it was deemed to be the plant of all
plants, the sacred plant. And that was
its status through all of at least 8,000
years and remains its status amongst
those who use the plant today. Today,
you know, if you watch indigenous people
using cocoa, very often they make what's
called a kinta, which is an offering.
They take three perfect leaves and put
them together in a fan shape and blow on
them and will whisper prayers to them.
And this is very common thing to
observe.
>> Well, it's more than that, Andy. When
people meet on the trail, they make they
make a cruseta of leaves and then they
lift it to the highest sacred mountain
blow up.
>> Wait, what is a cruseta? Just to provide
context for people.
>> A little cross of three leaves, three
perfect leaves, and you point it to the
mountain and then you blow the energy of
the leaf to the mountain. And the
metaphor is the energ leaf like in the
same way a cloud condenses to bring rain
and fertility to soil. So too this is
creating your sort of connection to to
to landscape and every single thing that
happens in the Andes a field is planted,
cocoa is sprinkled, tools are brought
back in the evening, cocoa is given to
them. Koka appears in as a symbol of the
social contract and the social nexus of
people. This is why it's so important,
as the anthropologist Katherine Allen
said, is that to deny people cocoa in
the Andes is not like denying the
Germans beer or the British tea or the
French coffee. It's actually an act of
cultural genocide because you cannot be
runa. You cannot be of the Andes of
Pchaamama if you do not use the leaves
and you must use them properly. And
nothing causes more offense than
tourists who stuff their leaves as the
people say like horses eating hay. And
in the Sierra Nevada Santa Marta where
the highest consumption of cocoa in the
world, men are constantly chewing hyo.
>> What is hyo?
>> Hao is a name of cocoa in Colombia. that
is ariththro novag granitensi a variety
novag granitensi which is a koka of
colombia and the cocoa used today by the
mammals of the sier no Santa Marta but
they contemplate the day to come they
contemplate the day that they've lived
you begin to chew leaves when you are of
an age to marry and so the chewing of
leaves is the expression of the essence
of who you are as a people and that
happens to be a culture that believes
that their prayers literally maintain
the cosmic balance of the world and So
in all these societies,
the act of chewing cocoa is an act of
being alive. And to be denied the use of
cocoa is to suffer a kind of existential
eradication that is complete. Now to be
fair, indigenous people throughout the
Americas
have the right to use cocoa in most
jurisdictions. But of course, the cost
of cocoa is skyrocketed with the illicit
market. And so there are many
communities where the tradition of using
cocoa is being lost simply because of
the price of the leaves.
But again, the issue for us, I think, in
our initiative is not just a traditional
use of leaf, but the right of all
peoples in all places in the world to
benefit from the incredible gift that
this plant represents. It's Latin
America's greatest gift to the world.
And it's one that's been denied in a way
that's been incredibly unproductive. I
guess potatoes are a pretty good gift,
too, right? So, let me come back. I
promised to do a call back to the
question that I had bookmarked. I mean
doing homework for this in conversation
with you guys also lots of text messages
and so on. I mean it seems like there
are many reasons that if one could wave
a magic wand to create elicit trade of
cocoa it would be a good idea. You would
have dramatic impact on indigenous land
rights. You would curtail deforestation
because things wouldn't be pushed to the
outer edges where they can be better
hidden. certainly the sustenance and
viability of these communities who are
already operating farms, not to mention
the potential global impact
if this were to be more widely
available, certainly pending or parallel
with lots more research, right? So,
there's a lot of good that could come of
it. Could these farms be converted to
legal trade without these farmers having
a bullseye painted on their head by
cartel who are dependent on them for
producing their product?
>> It's not as if the cartels are going to
roll over and say, "Oh, go great. Sell
your tea to Andy Wild Inc." On the other
hand, the point is that the cartels are
already out of control in Colombia and
doing what whatever they want anyway and
they will continue to grow cocoa as they
want to grow cocoa and continue to
produce enormous quantities of elicit
cocaine. Whether or not individuals will
be free to grow cocoa with impunity.
Obviously, there's going to be conflict.
If the state has an national interest in
the cultivation, illicit cultivation of
cocoa, they'll have an interest in
protecting those who are growing the
cocoa. It's not going to be some kind of
smooth transition. But the point is that
the situation in Colombia, for example,
is already completely chaotic with the
production having skyrocketed since the
peace agreement and parts of the country
now being inaccessible. And that's
really a failure of leadership by the
federal state. But I don't think that's
a reason not to move forward with
creating illicit product for the farm
families who you know have been waiting
for this.
>> Andy, maybe you could speak to this next
just to rotate here. What is the wedge
in the door, right? Because this would
be a big long-term undertaking, right,
to rehabilitate KOKA. So what are sort
of tangible next steps you think would
move the needle in a positive direction?
Is it funding research? Is it pilot
programs of some type for legal
products? What do you think?
>> I think it's got to be multironged. One
is creating consumer demand for it.
>> Creating a market in North America for
cocoa. If consumers want it, that will
move the needle quite a bit. Secondly,
there have to be FDA recognized approved
uses of it which there now are not and
that has to be demonstrated has to be
supported by research. Some obvious ones
are for the treatment of GI disorders
for treatment of substance abuse
disorders.
I think possibly for treatment of ADHD
for example with a much safer stimulant.
I think the metabolic indications that
there's great potential there that needs
some research to demonstrate that. But
if this shows potential for preventing
or treating type 2 diabetes, you know,
that would be enormous and I think we
can make a list of these things. So I
think it's we've got to work on all
these fronts, but to me the first thing
is making people aware of what cocoa is.
You know, most people don't know
anything about it, and if they do, they
just think of it as the source of
cocaine. So that's where we're starting.
There was a big effort and a very
hopeful effort to get the UN to reschedu
Koka. And this was done at the request
of both the Bolivian and the Colombian
governments. And the hope as I mentioned
was that KOKA would be taken out of
schedule. Andy mentioned as KO is in
schedule two in the United States, but
by the international
statutes of the UN is still schedule
one. And the goal was to try to get it
completely descheduled as a benign plant
that it is. The group that met in Vienna
decided against that to maintain the
status quo to the disappointment of all
advocates. And the rationale was a
little strange. The reason that cocoa
remained the equivalent of fentanyl is
that cocaine could be extracted from
cocoa. Well, everybody knows that. and
the fact that nothing stopped the
cartels extracting cocaine by the ton.
So it made no sense that logic but
because of that cocoa remains scheduled.
That was a big disappointment but that
effort continues. But we are seeing
movement in the US with you know there's
been movement with cannabis there's been
movement with psychedelics.
A lot of this has been I think promoted
by veterans demanding access to these
treatments for you know mental health
conditions but things finally have
loosened up and maybe as part of that
momentum we can introduce you know
discussions of koka and getting some
movement there as well. Yeah, I think
it's possible. My sort of pragmatic hat
is always wondering, well, if we have
many, many, many people listening to
this podcast, they're probably policy
makers. There are individuals certainly
who say to themselves, hey, I would love
to cut down on my coffee. Maybe give
cocoa a spin. Sounds mild.
Maybe doing a few days of that would be
wonderful. But I don't know what then
their next step is or how the demand or
interest is harnessed in a way that
leads to broader change. Do you have any
thoughts on getting specific
stakeholders to take any next steps?
Because chances are you have people from
every possible walk listening to this.
You likely have scientists who are
perhaps psychedelic adjacent. Maybe they
are stimulant adjacent who are
interested. Of course, it's a
fundraising question, but that's
solvable. I think I would be willing to
help fund some research. What else can
be done? Well, to the scientists, I
would say, you know, this is an
incredibly interesting plant with a
fascinating history, cultural relevance,
chemistry, pharmacological effects, and
it hasn't been studied. You know, it's
just waiting there. This would be a rich
subject for investigation. So I would
think that scientists who are curious
about things of this sort, medicinal
plants, medical botany, natural products
would want to take a look at this.
>> I'll just say because it's schedule two
versus schedule one, it makes the
presumably the process for researching
it much easier and much less expensive.
But I would say Tim to the entrepreneurs
who might be listening and that the
person who manages to crack this nut has
the potential to make enormous wealth
because I think the qualities of coco
are such that they could very easily
compete on the level that coffee is
presented to the world. It's just a much
much better natural stimulant, a more
effective one, a more benign one, a more
useful one. So when the dam breaks, it
will be enormous. And again, you have
issues of intellectual property, but
again, this is a plant that's been used
for 8,000 years by everybody. It's very
difficult for anyone to claim
the intellectual rights to this plant.
And as some good friends of mine say, in
this case, the plant itself has agency,
you know, and the plant wants to be
known to people.
>> And the other element of this is
storytelling. I mean, Andy and I are in
in midst of raising funds to make a film
that will celebrate in a positive sense
Koka and the whole tradition. And it's a
story of social justice. It's a story of
spiritual illumination. It's a story of
Andian prehistory.
Incredible story of cultural
celebration, ethnographic richness. And
I think if people embraced the story,
they would be deeply moved. And at the
same time, it's also a story of
incredible violation of human rights.
And the egregious way by which this
plant has been demonized speaks to
larger issues that we face as we try to
find a way to live on this planet. And
so I think it the story is so rich. And
Wade and I have been involved in an
effort to rehabilitate Koker for some
time. In the 1970s, I started a
notfor-profit foundation called the
Beneficial Plant Research Association,
whose aim was to
conduct research, make people aware of
lesserk known medicinal plants, and the
main one we focused on was Koka. We were
way ahead of our time, but we had
wonderful people involved in this
effort. And the group lapsed, but I
revived it a couple of years ago, and
it's now very robust. We have some
really great scientists behind it and I
would urge listeners to check our
website which is bp.org
and read about the Koka project and what
we are involved with.
>> bp.org.
Is that right?
>> Yeah.
>> If people were interested in potentially
supporting the film, is that where they
should go to contact folks?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. All right. That's one that people
can latch on to. Now Wade, you were
delivering a a summons, a call to action
to entrepreneurs. As luck would have it,
we may have an entrepreneur in our midst
known for True Food Kitchen, not only
Machakari. So Andrew, if you were going
to market and you're like, you know
what, let me pave the way. I'm not
saying that's your plan, but if you
decided, I want to be the first to
introduce
>> Koka, right? Kokari, you could come up
with, I'm sure that you could do a line
extension. Fantastic matcha for people
who are interested.
>> By the way, matcha and cocoa are both
green powders. So, I'm an advocate of
green powders. And [laughter] you know,
matcha, this is another one that I got
interested in way before its time. And I
tried for a number of years to introduce
it here unsuccessfully. And now it has
become I mean it is just unbelievable.
The worldwide demand for it has
completely stressed Japan's capacity to
produce it.
>> Yeah. So that took maybe 15 20 years for
me to get that going. Coke is probably
going to take a little longer, but I am
determined.
>> What would be the levers or perhaps
dominoes is a better metaphor that you
would want to tip over on the path to
introducing cocoa as a commercial
product. Even just one good study
clearly demonstrating one of these
effects that we've talked about
>> helping people get off much more
dangerous stimulants or regulating
carbohydrate metabolism, helping to
prevent type 2 diabetes.
Wade, what do you think?
>> Well, I think that focusing on what Andy
and I know from our personal experiences
is how fantastic Coke is, how it works.
I think all of us Tim as conscious human
beings suffer from these kind of
afflictions that the Buddhists talk
about you know the monkey mind the sort
of little moments of neurosis or even
depression.
>> Oh, you're lucky moments. Thank God I
would pay to have moments.
>> Yeah, exactly. And I'll say something
very personal. I mean I have two
daughters and both of them for different
reasons have been on some of these
serotonin uptake inhibitors. You know,
Prozac and Never Rolin. But you know, I
watched that and what I experienced in
my life, which is a very productive
life, is that I function perfectly well
without cocoa. Just like old Schulties
used to say, he chewed cocoa every day
in the Amazon. He didn't chew it in
Boston. I find that if I run out of
cocoa, my life goes on. It's just not as
nice a life and it's not as productive a
life. But what I find is that I'm as
susceptible as anybody to mood swings,
to existential despair, whatever we call
it. I think this is part of the human
condition. In the same way, the death is
the price we pay for the glory of being
alive. I think some of these little
mental fuckups are what we pay for for
the price of being conscious.
>> The tax,
>> it's like a tax,
>> ticket of entry. Yeah. And that's the
whole thing about cocoa is that it takes
care of that without having any sense
that you've been drugged or even
stimulated. You just find that stuff
flitting your way and it just makes for
a more productive life. I've written 24
books, Tim, and I made 50 films and
people, "Oh, he's so productive." And I
just smile like the sher cat. Of course
I am. And Andy knows exactly how and
why. I think probably Andy and I both
share a certain frustration that you
can't talk people into this. You know,
it's sort of show don't tell and it's so
subtle. I remember the first time I ever
really got behind coke. It was in the
PMO above Sandoi in Colombia and Tim and
I had gotten a bunch of leaves in Sylvia
and Tim was never one to rush a
situation that was itself inherently
pleasant. And so we just laid back in
the sun and I'd been with the mamos. I
mean, but I hadn't really discovered the
plant. I mean, Andy will tell you, you
create a learned experience with these
plants. And suddenly I just felt like I
was just where I wanted to be. And
that's what Andy says when Andy, and
I've quoted him many times, first went
to the Cubo in it was 73, wasn't it
Andy?
>> Yeah. And there's a beautiful passage in
one of Andy's essays where he exposed to
Mambbe for the first time. Mambbe by the
way for the audience is just an
Amazonian form of cocoa. It becomes a
green powder like matcha and you don't
use it with an ad mixture. The ad
mixture is the ash is placed in the
preparation. So you end up swallowing
the whole the whole thing and you absorb
the nutrients and so on. But anyway, so
Andy had been exposed to Momb. And the
next day with the men, they gather
around this calabash and he walks away
as I walked away in the Northwest Amazon
with a spring to your feet, oblivious to
the humidity, as Andy said in that
wonderful passage, swinging my machete
and feeling that I was just where I
wanted to be. And I think that's a
really great summation of the subjective
effects of Koko. And can I say I
attribute at least some of my well-being
to regular use of cocoa.
>> By the [clears throat] way, today is my
birthday and I am 84.
>> Oh, happy birthday.
>> And I feel pretty good.
>> Yeah, you look great.
>> Oh, yeah. People always comment on how
good I look and so forth and I I have to
say cocoa has contributed to that.
All right, [clears throat] I have many
more questions, but I'll I'll try to
contain I could probably use some more
cocoa to get this ADHD, OCD under
control, but are there for people who
have heard and maybe latched on to
something you said earlier, which is one
good scientific study. Yeah,
>> I'm a firm believer in this because I've
been very active on trying to establish
firsts pilots that might be a proof of
concept that then catalyze more research
etc. Are there any particular
researchers who people could look to
fund?
>> Let me mention one who is on our board
of beneficial plants and that's Chris
Mccertie who is a medicinal
pharmacologist at the University of
Florida.
>> How do you spell the last name? MC
capital curd d y Chris mccertie he's
University of Florida
>> and he is the main person who's
researched
>> and has a lot of federal support for his
studies of
>> kraton and I met with him and got him
interested in koka
>> and he was determined to you know do a
study of this now I will just tell you
it has been a very torturous route for
him to get leaves legally to study but
he finally just this week got his supply
I You would not believe the red tape.
>> Why is it so hard?
>> Because this is the problem with Koka,
you know, that it's just all these
regulations and fear about it and
confusion with cocaine. Anyway, he's a
very interesting person to talk to, but
he is set up. He's just about to get
going and he's doing animal research
first, but is using whole cocoa trying
to disentangle the effects of the
different alkyoids. But one of his
interests is looking at this possibility
of of regulating carbohydrate
metabolism.
>> So he's the main person at the moment
that I know who is doing research in
this area and he's very good.
>> Yeah. I was wondering I looked him up
while we were talking.
>> Might not be a fit, might be a fit, but
Dr. Peter Hris has done some interesting
work perhaps best known for looking at
the potential use of psilocybin combined
with psychotherapy as a promising
treatment for cocaine use disorder. So
there might be room for looking at, as
strange as it might sound to people,
cocoa for cocaine use disorder. That
might be too hard to sell.
>> I proposed that in an article that I
wrote long ago saying that this would be
one of the possible uses to wean people
off of cocaine onto cocoa. That would be
a big step up. I had not even thought
about and I feel foolish realized that
even if it's schedule two if you are say
using methylenadate aka rolin or
something else you just synthesize the
damn stuff whereas if you have to get
actual organic cocoa leaves that adds a
whole different layer of headache in
terms of procuring it because now you're
dealing with importation and this that
and the other thing yeah I hadn't even
thought about that wrinkle there's
always a wrinkle
>> right Okay, got it. And for someone like
Christopher McCertie, how much do
research studies like this cost? Do you
have any ballpark for folks? In my
experience, it's like, okay, the number
of subjects determines a lot of the
cost. So, if you want to power the
study, if you want to try to get a
properly powered study, maybe you want
to increase the scope, right, for more
people to participate, etc. But do you
have any idea, and I know you're not
speaking for him, but do you have any
idea what something like that might
cost?
>> More than you would think. [laughter]
So, you know, that is a challenge. But,
you know, Chris has found that the
federal government, National Institute
on Drug Abuse, is willing to fund these
studies. So, that's very promising.
>> Yeah. I had Nora Vulov of Naida on the
podcast a couple years ago and it was a
really good conversation and she was in
the I think this don't know if this is
public might have to scratch it but she
was in the oval office
>> for the executive order related to
psychedelics and I was like man that's
awesome
>> and she's so brilliant so I don't know
what her current status is within Naida
she might still be running it
>> but there seems to be a sea change a
foot
>> yes
>> so the timing could be very
serendipitous, right, to try to kick
something off now, particularly on the
research front. Okay. Yeah. For people
who might be wondering, I'll just throw
out some numbers. I mean, early on, this
2015, helping to fund some of the
initials psilocybin studies looking at
depression at Hopkins. I mean, for 50k,
you could make a huge, huge, huge
difference.
>> Really, that's great.
>> It's not necessarily millions of people.
It depends on Again,
the size, the ambition, and you don't
want to be pennywise and pound foolish,
right? If you can fund more and you want
to drive the possibility for
statistically meaningful outcome that is
suitable for publishing and defensible,
then maybe you write a bigger check,
right? Especially if you're going to
wait all that time because science is
pretty slow when it's done properly.
>> Wade, what can you tell us anything
about what's going on in Canada? because
the regulations in Canada are a little
more favorable than they are in the US
and there are some research interests up
there.
>> There's nothing really definitive. I
mean, I think one opening in the States
could be Bobby Kennedy. I've been with
Bobby, few people know, but when his
father was killed, was sent by the
family to Colombia and he fell in love
with Colombia. And I've been in Colombia
with Bobby with the Mamos chewing cocoa.
He totally understands the plant and he
certainly understands the distinction
between cocoa and the alkyoid cocaine.
So I think there's an opening there
which could be very promising.
>> And one area that I very much agree with
him on is his initiative to change
psychiatry and move it away from you
know the biomedical model which I think
has been really failed us. Mhm.
>> I mean, I think this whole Koka story,
you slam up against the whole kind of
failure of the war on drugs and the
ideology of the war on drugs. There's a
very funny account where in October, end
of October 2020, there was this bust at
the Philadelphia International Airport
of 15 pounds of what was called green
cocaine. And the customs agents sort of
heralded this great sign of the
vigilance of their colleagues and so on,
you know, and anyone who knew anything
about anything could see that that green
cocaine was Mambi. And also in the bus
was a brown paste which everybody knew
would have been a tobacco paste. Now
tobacco kills 400,000 people every year,
but it's legal. So this was not of
concern to the agents, but the green
cocaine was. and they analyzed it and
discovered it had some cocaine in it,
trivial amounts, so that if anyone had
tried to snort the mambbe, they just
sort of plugged their nose most
unpleasantly with a powder the
consistency of talcum powder. But the
thing that was so disturbing about the
bust is that after 60 years of war on
drugs, you had customs agents who still
didn't know the difference between cocoa
and cocaine after [clears throat]
expending a trillion dollars on this
failed campaign. And that was really the
equivalent, if you think about it, of
Elliot Nest busting a truckload of
potatoes in violation of the Volstead
Act. You know, cocoa is to cocaine what
potatoes are to vodka.
>> That's a good comparison. I like that.
>> Or a peach. We don't deny us the right
to enjoy the luscious fruit of a peach
because of the cardioactive glycosides
found within the pit of every peach. Not
to kind of push the metaphor, but
they're truly apples and oranges. And so
I think when you combine that kind of in
the- moment idiocy together with the
really pernitious history by which this
plant has been demonized, I mean Andy
said earlier that these countries remain
countries of conquered and conqueror and
in this era where we're so sensitive to
language. If people were aware of the
language and I wrote a long piece for
Rolling Stone called the secret history
of Koka, the language being used by
those who crafted the very documents
that we live by to this day is so
hideous that it would cause anybody to
be immediately dismissed from any
position in our country today. And yet
that language accusing ki users of being
pornog. I mean you can't because they
make this stuff up. And it was all
driven by the same guy Enslinger who
gave us reefer madness. And so we're
still living by that mindset which has
been utterly exposed as a racist and
colonial conceit that it was. I think
that Koka is the most perfect example of
how we've gone wrong in our relations
with the natural world. You know, really
failing to see that plant for what it
is, confusing it with this one component
of it, and then getting ourselves in
enormous amounts of trouble. And in my
career as a physician, I have worked for
years and years to help people
understand the differences between whole
plants, natural products, and isolated
compounds. I mean, I think isolated
compounds have their place in medicine,
but very often I see that these complex
natural mixtures work better, are much
safer, often have effects that we don't
have pure compounds that work for. And
Coke is a perfect example of that. And
Andy, when you say that, you know,
relation to the natural world in a
social sense,
>> y
>> it's expressed in Peru as well. I mean,
one of the great rituals I've
participated in is called the muimeto.
It's out of Cusco, where once each year,
the fastest young boy in every hamlet is
given the gift of becoming a woman. And
he has to lead all able-bodied men on
this ritual run. But it's not your
ordinary run. You start off at 11,500
ft, run down to to the base of the
sacred mountain to 9,000 ft. Then you
run to over 16,000 ft, and you fall over
two across soaring Andian ridges over
the course of this 24-hour race, it's
less a race than a ritual of ordeal. And
the idea is that as you enter this race
through pure exhaustion, you make the
sacrifice that makes it sacred from the
Latin. And I did that race at the age of
48, the oldest man ever to do it and the
only outsider to do it. And I only got
through that race by chewing more cocoa
in one day than anyone in the 8,000 year
history of the planet. But the point is
what Andy is saying about our relation
with the natural world. What that race
is really about is expressing a sense of
obligation and belonging. You're running
the perimeter of the lands. There's
sacred mounds of earth, hiktos, mahones,
where the waka must spin to bring the
energy of the woman to the mountaintop
where coke is given to patcha mama. And
so the race becomes a ritual of
belonging. You're demonstrating your
ownership but also your obligation to
preserve that land. So you see koka in
that sense is as powerful and adjunct to
culture
as Iaska might be amongst the peoples of
the anaconda. You know, you can't do
that run without Koka. Tim and Koka is
the mediator. You know, they often say
that the first to taste the leaves was
Antisima Maria in the kind of syncric
myth of origins. When she lost the
Christ child and her grief, she sampled
the leaf and that gave her the spirit to
continue. Well, obviously that's a
syncric fusion of pre-Colombian and
Catholic ideas, but that's an indicator
of its centrality
in the stream of existence in the Andes.
>> So, let me ask just a personal question
of you guys which I'm sure has occurred
to a lot of listeners or viewers and
that is like why why do you care so much
about this in the hierarchy of reasons
like what's at the top? What is it for
you Andy? For me, it is the confusion of
a plant with an element of it, which is
I think a problem that I see in medicine
greatly that we just fail to understand
those differences. And I would like to
help educate more people about that.
[clears throat]
>> And as I said, I think Koka
>> is a most perfect example
>> of how we've gone wrong in our
relationship with a plant.
>> And also just to underscore one thing
which is not what you're saying. You
were not saying that all plants are
therefore safe, right? That whole plants
are therefore like you don't want to go
out and start chugging a bunch of
hemlock tea. Right.
>> Right. There's plenty of stuff. However,
>> piece versus whole, component versus
entire plant are different. They are
just different.
>> That's a big one. By the way, in our
society particularly, I think there is
great fear of nature and we tend to see
nature as hostile. I many people I know
think if you just go out and randomly
munch plants in your backyard, you'll
likely die. You know, the percentage of
plants that can seriously harm you is
pretty small. I mean, there aren't many
hemlocks out there,
>> right?
>> There's a lot of things that don't taste
good. There's a lot of things that might
give you an upset stomach, but there's
not a lot of things that can kill you or
cause serious harm. I once had dinner
with the chief technical adviser to one
of the big European supplement companies
and he was Austrian. He had traveled all
over the world and he said that one
thing that struck him was the extreme
fear of nature in the English-speaking
world. I mean I'd never heard anyone say
that but he said this is an attitude
that he found very common in the UK and
Canada and Australia and the US New
Zealand. And he said very different to
what you see for example in German
speakaking Europe where people tend to
regard nature as friendly, benign,
helpful and you know in German
[clears throat] culture there's great
use of medicinal plants and natural
forms very different from what we have
here. So that's just an interesting
perspective. I'd never noticed that
before.
>> Where do you think that comes from? Any
ideas?
>> I wonder. Wade any suggestions?
>> I know. You certainly see it amongst,
you know, fungalophobes as you always
talk about Andy, you know, the fear of
mushrooms.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, but Kim, back to your
question, you know, for me, I rever
because of what it's done for my life,
but also it symbolizes for me everything
I care about in terms of culture as an
anthropologist and everything I've ever
fought for in terms of the rights of
indigenous people. And it's to me one of
the most egregious violations of the
rights of other cultures. And it's also
a denial of the genius of other
cultures. So it sort of symbolizes for
me everything that I've stood up against
in my career. And it happens to be a
plant that has brought benefits to me,
enormous benefits. But I'll give you if
I could share one anecdote
>> of course
>> that shows how crazy this all is is that
I don't know if you remember but some
years ago Peru qualified for the first
time in 10 years for the World Cup and I
saw the victory match on a screen in
Cusco was played in Lima and then the
captain of the Peruvian team who played
for a squad in Sao Paulo in a random
drug test was shown to have metabolites
of cocaine in his urine and he was going
to be kicked off the team and this was
going to make a huge international
scandal and his lawyer called me from Sa
Paulo. And I said, "Well, wait a minute.
Doesn't he come from Lima?" "Yeah."
"Well, they just went through Christmas,
didn't he go to Ayakucho or Cusco?"
"Yeah." "Oh, he must have stayed at the
Monestario Hotel in Cusco cuz that's the
nicest hotel." "Yeah, that's where he
stayed." Well, that hotel has huge vats
of coca tea available at all times for
its clientele for altitude sickness. And
that's what he had done. He had drunk
copious amounts of coca tea. And because
of the idiocy of our understanding of
the difference between the plant and the
drug, this could have been an
international incident because you well
know that Peruvians, like all Latin
Americans, take their football very
seriously.
>> Yeah.
>> But we got it off.
>> Yeah. Very seriously. Andy, it looked
like you were going to say something. Do
you have anything to add to that?
>> Nope. I think for different reasons. We
come from different places. We both are
very passionate about this issue.
>> Coke has always seemed to be defined as
what it is not. It's not cocaine. And
you know, presenting this plant in all
of its kind of glory. I mean, it's
interesting, you know, I mean, Andy's a
real plant guy. He's a real
ethnobbotonist, a real physician who's
always had plants in his practice. And I
went through a period of time where I
was very much a botanical explorer. But
I'm fundamentally a storyteller, a
writer, an anthropologist. But this
plant wrapped its arms around me when I
was 19 years old and has never let me
go. And I have a kind of deep fidelity.
It's hard to explain. I don't normally
speak in this kind of language, but this
plant has given me so much and has
allowed me to explore and have such
extraordinary experiences in the field
in pursuit of its mysteries and its
wonder that I feel that liberating Koka
is the final act of my professional
life. I feel that very sincerely and it
also brings me back to Andy because Andy
was like always my big brother you know
Andy and Tim Plowman who were great
friends both acolytes of Schulties and
for me I was able to come along as their
kind of kid brother so the relationship
with Andy to me is enormously important
emotionally spiritually even and if Andy
and I in the memory of Tim who
tragically died way too young at the age
of 45 the great botanical authority on
Koka uh he died of AIDS and incidentally
as I was reading and doing his eulogy
that I conceived the book one river
which is a biography of our great
professor Richard Evans Schulties. We're
doing this in part in memory of Tim. I'm
sure Andy would agree.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Well, I we've covered a lot of
ground. What I'm going to do also to try
to consolidate next steps for people for
anyone listening or watching is I'll
create tim.blog/ccoa.
So on my website
>> that would be great. that'll lead to
this episode. And at the very top of the
show notes, we'll have a link to the
bp.org. We'll have a link to some of the
researchers who were mentioned,
including any others that you guys might
think of after the fact.
>> That'd be great. We would most
appreciate that.
>> Well, it would be wonderful. A link to
some of the pieces that Andy and I have
written would be really great. That
would be wonderful.
>> Yeah, for sure. We'll put a bunch of
stuff at the top with a bias for people
who are listening. If they're like,
"This is all great. I don't want to be
purely a passive consumer of education
or edutainment." Like, I actually want
to put a dent in the world, then we'll
have that at the top because I don't
want to bury that stuff in terms of
possible next actions for people, folks.
That'll be at tim.log/ccoa.
Just like Coca-Cola. Not a coincidence,
by the way.
>> Yeah, [laughter]
>> I'll read you. This is a piece on Eater.
People can look it up. Maybe I'll link
to it actually. An unassuming set of
buildings in Maywood, New Jersey, less
than 10 miles from Manhattan, holds a
surprising secret. It's what might be
arguably called the cocaine capital of
the United States. Here, a chemical
company manufactures cocaine legally
with a special permission from the US
government. All in service of a familiar
company, Coca-Cola. Cola, by the way,
just for people who like little bits of
trivia, comes from Cola Ka. Well, in
English at least, African known for its
caffeine content.
>> Correct.
>> So, there you go. Coca-Cola. And by the
way, Tim, Coca-Cola notoriously had a
secret cocoa plantation in Hawaii.
>> Hawaii. Yeah.
>> No kidding.
>> Yeah.
>> Scoundrels. Look at that.
>> And you know that is the only legal
export of cocoa from Peru is to that
chemical company, Steen Chemical, in
Maywood, New Jersey. And the cocaine is
extracted and sold for pharmaceutical
use. And the rest of the leaves are made
into an extract which is a secret
flavoring ingredient in Coca-Cola.
>> And what's more, in the in the 1961 UN
Convention on Narcotic Drugs, there was
one specific
exclusion of Kulka solely for that
company. And I got to go in Peru to
where they were getting their leaves
from. And they were trashy leaves. I
mean, it was literally the sweepings of
the floor. stuff that Wade and I would
not chew. [laughter]
>> Drinking sawdust.
>> Yeah.
>> Botanical sawdust.
Well, another bit of u trivia for folks
if they care. Seven Up used to contain
lithium citrate.
>> Oh, yes. Right. Right.
>> Back in the day, you know, those old
soda companies had some stuff figured
out.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, gentlemen, is there anything else
before we start to wind to a close that
you would like to add? Certainly. I
would love you guys to mention where
people can find you online if you'd like
them to go in any particular direction
and anything else that you would like to
add. Andy?
>> Sure. My website is dr.com.
drwiel.com.
There's a lot of health information
there. And I am the founder of the
Andrew Wild University of Arizona Center
for Integrative Medicine. We train
physicians and health professionals. on
that website is awcim.org
and I'm very proud of our work there.
We've graduated almost 3,000 physicians
and allied health professionals from our
very intensive trainings which include
really good instruction on botanical
medicine.
>> I love it. And people can also find you
on Instagram X etc. Dr. Wild and
presumably you don't have a tap into the
back of your brain for that. I'm sure
there's nice good publishing of valuable
content coming out there so people can
check that out. And then Wade
>> I just wanted to say Tim if I could just
insert this in case you could use it is
that I've made a lot of reference to the
egregious language by those who's
responsible for the language of the UN
declaration. Mhm.
>> But maybe I could just read the key
figure was an acolyte of antser who was
notorious anti-drug warrior that we
almost joke about with reefer madness.
>> But this man name was Pablo Oswaldo
Wolf. He was a chief of the addiction
producing drugs section of the World
Health Organization. He not only
conceived, he wrote the language of Koka
demonization in that. But listen to what
he says and this is from a lecture to
the Royal Society of Medicine in London
on the very eve of that commission led
by Fonda going to Peru.
The India who does not chew cocoa leaves
is clearsighted, intelligent and
light-hearted, willing to work, vigorous
and resistant to diseases. The cockro on
the contrary is apathetic, lazy,
insensitive to his environment. His mind
is befoged. His emotional reactions are
rare and violent. He is morally and
intellectually enesticized, socially
subdued, almost a slave. Moral
degeneration accompanies the physical.
Lying is one of the outstanding
characteristics, probably due to a lack
of moral equilibrium. Criminality is
high and barbaric forms of homicide can
only be explained by a certain moral
insensibility.
We are convinced that cocoa leaf chewing
is a social evil. The chronic
consumption of these leaves constitutes
a social poison which undermines the
physical and mental health of the
population. The children of cockeros are
markedly deficient in intelligence.
There is no doubt that the habit of
chewing coke leaves is one of the most
powerful reasons for the backwardness
and misery of the Indian population. The
last link in a chain of social and
medical scourges which include
popperism, bad housing conditions,
deficient nutrition, rudimentary or
completely absent education, alcoholism,
tuberculosis, venerial disease and other
infections and promiscuity to mention
only the worst calamities and miseries.
>> I never heard that, Wade. I never heard.
>> It's quite a list of offenses. This is
quoted in my Rolling Stone piece, Andy.
You just can't believe the language. The
remedy of the moment is gradual dis
intoxication of the native, diminishing
the production as well as the
consumption of cocoa by means of a
suitable education by abolishing the
superstition of the magic action and the
well-being of the leaves by prohibiting
initiation of young, you know, goes on
and on. Only with skill and patience can
cocoa addiction be abolished. But it can
be done. Christianized Indians no longer
live in the former wretched conditions
and thus show themselves physically and
mentally capable of freeing themselves
from cocoa leaf chewing and addictions.
And you have to think this is the man
who wrote the statutes that we turn to
today in the 1961 UN Convention on
Narcotic Drugs. This is the language
that the UN World Health Organization
has recently affirmed by refusing to
deschedu or reschedu Koka.
>> Might be time for an update.
>> Yeah,
>> it's that bad. Now, can you think of any
other policy that we would live by
today? It's like policies have been
written by I don't know Herman Goran or
Google dictating you know religious
policies today in the United States of
America and yet this is what we are
trying to deal with and confront and it
is so dark and so evil. Well, it sounds
like a terrible b time for an update. C
I'm sure a lot of the people who are
adjacently or indirectly affirming this
have no idea what it actually says,
right? They have not
>> read what you just read aloud. So worth
another look like a lot of things. And
not saying it's a panacea, not saying
that
there shouldn't be guide rails or guard
rails, but that it's worth another look.
And I do think the wedge in the door to
pull from language earlier probably is a
awareness of the benefits. And I think
you guys do a pretty damn fine job of
showcasing the longitudinal productivity
gains
[laughter]
of of moderate sustained use and
separately getting some science funded
and I think those are parallel tracks.
>> Yeah. and the [snorts] film itself being
used as an educational tool to support I
would say both of those, right? The
latter and the scientific exploration
>> because it strikes me. I mean, look, I'm
not a doctor. I don't play one on the
internet, nor am I a scientist, but I I
like to spend time with a lot of
scientists. It's like I I think about
some of the effects of cocoa and the
appetite suppression, but the physical
vigor in the absence of food, and I
wonder, man, I would love to just take
blood ketone measurements of these
people.
>> Simple stuff.
>> I mean, so simple. So, so, so
straightforward.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, guys, this has been wonderful. Any
last closing comments, concerns,
complaints?
>> Thank you for providing a forum to talk
about this. My pleasure.
>> I would like to add Andy just one
comment in which Kim just said and what
you responded how easy these experiments
could have been done. Yeah. And I think
we have to remember that it's not an
accident that they weren't done.
>> In other words, the nutritional study
that you and Tim did in 1970s could have
been done in the 1920s. It wasn't done
because people did not want anything
that would affirm the possibility that
the plant was anything but the demonic
entity that they claimed it to be. So,
it's important in all of this to
remember this wasn't just sort of an
accident of history or a casual neglect.
This was a conscious attempt to demonize
and eradicate a plant and not for
pharmarmacological reasons, not for
medical reasons, not for social reasons,
for cultural and political and reasons
of power.
>> Yeah. I wouldn't want to by association
[clears throat] make policy makers feel
like they need to carry the burden of
what was truly uh travesty if they are
in part those whose help we would we
would like but understanding the history
is important. I mean we'll link to the
Rolling Stone piece and also Andy
anything else that you would like linked
for people who want to check it out at
tim.blog/coka.
I mean cocoa has been of incredible
interest to me for decades now. It is of
such cultural importance. It is of
ecological importance.
>> Economic importance.
>> Economic importance. If you care about
conservation, if you care about
indigenous land rights, if you care
about health and performance, period.
Yeah. Let's say you don't give a damn
about what happens in South America, but
you just
>> say, "Wow, I feel like pounded dog [__]
after three cups of coffee and then I
can't sleep at night and then I'm
dependent and I have a headache when I
try to stop." It's worth digging a
little deeper and educating yourself on
cocoa. It may not be available tomorrow,
may not be available next year, but it
is [snorts] deeply deeply interesting
and endlessly fascinating as a possible
subject or focus of experiments. So,
I will leave it at that for now. We can
always and I'm sure we'll be chatting
more via text, but thank you guys very
much. Oh, and I would be remiss if I
didn't remind you,
Wade, that people can find you at
daviswade.com. Is that right?
>> Yeah, that that's my website.
>> That's the main place. Anywhere else you
would like to point people? We got Wade
Davis official on Instagram, exauthor
Wade Davis. Yeah,
>> I think people would be intrigued by the
book One River, which is really the
account of Tim and I and Koka and
Schulties.
>> It's a great book. It is a great book.
>> That book in particular would open
people's eyes.
>> Yeah. Perfect. All right. Check out One
River, folks.
>> Tim, again, we're grateful for your
support. Uh it can make a big
difference.
>> Very much so.
>> My pleasure. My pleasure.
>> Yeah. Thanks so much, Tim. Very
grateful.
>> This is important stuff. And it's also
while I have this before AI gobbles
every podcast I would like to surface
subjects that are of importance that
have not yet been reputationally
derisked.
>> I don't have to report to any corporate
overlord who can fire me or throttle my
sponsors or whatever it might be. So I
have the incredible accidental luxury of
being able to and joy of being able to
have these conversations with folks like
the two of you who are bringing in
decades of of expertise and research. So
always appreciate the time. Always nice
to see you both. And for people
listening as always show notes check it
out. tim.blogca blog/ccoa
will go straight to this episode and
give you more information on where you
can learn more. And until next time, be
just a bit kinder than is necessary to
others and to yourself. Compassion, oh
yeah, that applies to yourself, too.
Don't forget that. And as always, thanks
for tuning in.